STD Vector in C++ probably one of the
most useful tools in the entire language
and yet so much can go wrong in this
video we're going to talk about STD
Vector we're going to talk about how
I've seen it be used incorrectly so to
speak not necessarily incorrectly and
we'll get more into what I mean even by
that in the first place but there are
certain things that you need to be aware
of and certain ways that you might be
able to improve the way that you use it
and SCD Vector in C++ is a container
type that comes with a Santa template
Library the library of the actual
language it's a dynamically resizable
container of elements stored
continuously in memory it's basically
just like a normal array that we know
and love however the size can change
dynamically and that's what makes it
super useful and super dangerous so why
is it called Vector no idea some guy
Alex just decided it should be and then
later regretted it typical stuff for C++
now I have made videos as part of my C++
series talking about how to use an SD
Vector in the first place I'll have that
video linked up there that's from like I
don't even want to know how long that
video is like 6 years old probably now I
do want to mention what inspired this
video here was this code review that I
did this is my most recent code review
of a Tetris clone that someone sent in
someone called Adam and around 31
minutes into the video or so I'm talking
about this function over here which we
have over here which we will take a look
at more deeply later in this video and
this is just one example of something
that I see fairly often and it's very
very easy to improve it to just elevate
it up to the next level so that's what
we're going to talk about today now
speaking of elevating to the next level
you're learning.org the sponsor of this
video has a 30-day free trial that you
can check out to take a look at all of
the courses on their platform for free
for those of you who don't know
brilliant is an amazing website filled
with lots and lots of really high
quality courses on various stem topics
if you are just getting started with
programming and computer science they're
one of my most recommended resources
because I really like the fact that they
just teach you how to think like a
programmer instead of getting bogged
down in some specific language that's
not that important in the big picture
what you want to be able to do is think
in code you want to be able to reason
like a programmer and with their
extremely fun engaging and interactive
way of teaching you'll quickly find that
it's a super effective way to learn and
you'll actually retain and memorize this
information but then of course once
you've learned those Basics that strong
Foundation you can progress onto an
actual programming language like python
again with the same method of teaching
that's super effective and all of this
also extends into their wonderful math
courses which again go all the way down
to the beginner level but then into way
more advanced topics such as algebra and
calculus and as I mentioned you can get
started for free they have a 30-day free
trial that you can use brilliant all/
the chal link will be in description
below just work your way through some of
their courses see if you like them and
if you do then that link will also get
you 20% off a premium annual
subscription huge thank you to
brilliant.org as always for sponsoring
this video okay so first off before we
get into how to actually use SD Vector
let's talk about what kind of like
metric or criteria I'm actually using
here to Define what exactly is a better
way to use it what exactly is an
improvement because it's something that
obviously comes with the language and
people have been using it well in
whatever way fits their needs and
everything's been fine so what on Earth
am I talking about about when I say stop
using it badly stop using it incorrectly
and improve the way that you use it here
one word performance now SD vector and
in fact the entire s template library is
probably not something you necessarily
want to use if performance is of the
utmost importance usually what one might
do is write their own data structure
that suits their needs exactly or they
can use something else that someone else
has written such as eastl for example
eastl is EA's version of the standard
template Library that's more optimized
for game development and Speed and
Performance especially on certain
platforms back in the day we're not
going to get into that now that was
something that I used pretty often back
when I worked at EA but now they've made
it available on GitHub for anyone to use
so I'll have a link to that down in the
description below lots of Alternatives
out there but this is something that I'm
personally familiar with because I used
to work at EA so the standard template
Library not necessarily optimized for
Speed and for say like real time running
applications like games or game engines
but that being being said sometimes it's
more than enough if you just use it in a
way that prioritizes performance a
little bit better and that's what we're
going to be talking about today so step
one in the how to use SD Vector is don't
use it yeah pretty funny but what I'm
talking about is you need to ask
yourself whether or not it's the right
data structure for you now I will say
without a doubt that the simple array in
programming is the most used data
structure I don't think anyone can argue
with that if you want to argue with that
take it up in the comments below and I'm
talking about any array I'm talking
about a sequence of elements of any
defined or variable size that are stored
contiguously in memory and that last
part continuously in memory that's the
importance of this data structure data
structures are data structures they're
the way the data is structured where in
memory and that's why memory is so
critical to all of this however there
are two specific ways that you can
create an array of let's just say fixed
size in C++ and that comes down to the
two different types of memory that you
can use to actually store your data and
that is the stack and the Heap STD
Vector its job is the Heap that I think
is super important to realize the fact
that the difference between STD vector
and STD array is not just the fact that
STD array is just like a normal array
meaning you create it with a fixed size
and that's it you can't change the size
of it anymore but meanwhile Vector is
resizable you can just keep adding
elements to it that's the most critical
difference between the data structures
like superficially like at a user level
but internally the biggest difference is
the fact that SD array is stored on the
stack and SD Vector is stored on the
Heap and we know or at least we should
know that Heap is slower than stack I
have a video about this as well from
many years ago that I will link up there
and so what that means is that even if
you could use an STD Vector anywhere
where you could use SD array because you
don't have to use the resize ability
aspect of it and obviously it can store
well any number of you know fixed
elements or whatever that you need you
should always prioritize to use SD
because it is stored in memory that is
effectively faster faster to both
allocate and use so a good example of
this is from this Tetris clone code
review if we have a look at the actual
code over here this is the colors. URLs
over here if you guys want to check this
out as well and I had a lot to say about
the code in the specific file in that
code review so check it out if you're
interested but this is a perfect example
over here we have a function called get
cell colors that returns a vector right
and what do you think this function
returns well if we look at the CPP file
it returns a vector of all of these
elements do we know how many elements
there are yes do we need to Heap
allocate a vector of these elements
every time we call this function no does
this even need to be a function no but
that's a different story this is a great
example of where you should just use SD
array with the size of eight because
there are eight colors over here so this
is a great example of think about
whether or not you actually need to use
it because your priority should be to
not use it if you can avoid it and use
STD array instead now for step two I
guess onwards I haven't really planned
this out that well I have this little
program that I've written here in Visual
Studio that demonstrates how one might
use this Vector this is somewhat
inspired by the code from that code
review and specifically this function
over here inside the block. cppp file
and we'll probably Circle back to this
in the end just to give a more real
world example but over here I've just
written a little program that
demonstrates some of the usages of
vector as well as some incorrect things
that we'll correct so here we have a
vector of data what is data or data I'm
sorry if you guys prefer data I say data
sorry I'm Australian this is just a
super basic struct it just has one
integer in it called value it's just
supposed to represent something a little
bit more you know complex less trivial
than just like an INT if I made a vector
of ins over here we simply push back
five different integers here they're
ascending from 0 to four and then
there's this print vector function that
takes in a vector prints its size and
then all of the elements nicely so if I
just run this program as a baseline this
is the result we got five elements in
our vector and here they are so what I
want to do here is take a deeper look at
how memory is working here and
specifically the allocation of memory
how many allocations do we think we have
here well to do that in a really easy
kind of hacky way we'll say you can just
write a function right here in this file
called void operator new we'll take in
size T size that's how much we want to
allocate and we'll just return Malik
size this overrides the new operator
which the vector will'll use internally
to allocate memory and of course the
benefit here is we can add some of our
code and specifically what I'm going to
do is add a static int called allocation
count over here which I'll start at zero
and every time we allocate I'll
increment it and then also for fun I
might print you know the fact that we
allocated x amount of bytes over here
down here at the very end of our program
before we turn terminate I'm just going
to print out how many allocations we
have so s allocation count and now let's
run this eight
allocations eight allocations of memory
and yes they are all coming from the
vector class now here's an even cooler
thing what we can do is we can actually
set a breakpoint inside this function if
you want to dig deeper and see exactly
what is allocating that memory so if I
put a breakpoint here and I run the
program you can see we've hit the
breakpoint and over here in our call
stack we've got some external code if we
just right click and show external code
then you can see that we're going
through the SCD the standard template
Library over here from Main into vector
and Vector is going to do this thing
called Alec proxy it's just going to set
up like the allocator basically for this
I'm pretty sure that only happens in
debug so let's just hit F5 again and
over here we have sure in place one it
back and allocate and I'm not going to
go too deep into this but if you want to
you can see that you can now if I run
this in release quickly just to see if
we get perhaps one less allocation two
less allocations okay six allocations
but still six allocations you know how
many we should have for this program one
we should have one allocation so let's
have a look at what went wrong so first
and foremost this is a very easy one
don't copy vectors unless you need to
obviously but if you don't don't copy
vectors so over here I have the print
Vector function it takes in a vector and
you can see that there's no Amper sand
to be found nowhere in sight so you need
to add an amp and and this is we're only
reading here anyway obviously so we'll
add a const reference here and what that
means is that we're not going to be
copying the entirety of the vector and
making a brand new one copying in all of
the elements just to print them here for
no reason we can just use this original
vector and reference it so with that
we're down to five allocations this same
concept by the way doesn't just apply to
when you feed in a vector as a parameter
into a function it's the same exact
concept if you're trying to do something
like this within a function right if I'm
trying to reference this Vector but I'm
not creating a const reference then I am
making a copy of it example from the
Tetris game we have this tiles Vector
that we're creating and we're copying
this cells out a particular rotation
State into here we're making a brand new
Vector here allocating memory copying
all of the elements into here for what
just to iterate through them and then
push back these new positions into
another Vector right so there's no
reason why this has to be copied this
should just be a const reference if you
want to use tar as an alias now the next
thing is do you know how many elements
you're planning to have in that Vector
this doesn't even have to be an exact
amount it might be like some kind of
Maximum estimate because the way that
vectors work with their resizing is
somewhat annoying every compiler has
their own C++ Library basically right so
GCC has their own clang has their own
and msvc visual studio that's what we're
using here here they have their own
implementation basically of the C++
standard library in msvc what happens is
that every time you try and push back an
element into a vector and you don't have
the capacity for it right so initially
when we create this Vector we actually
have the ability to store zero elements
surprise when we push back the first one
it's like ah I need to grow I need to
resize so what does it do well in the
case of the first element that we push
back it just makes the size one but if
we go beyond that it will grow by 50% so
if you have two elements you'll get
three or rather room for three if you
have 10 you'll suddenly grow to 15 clang
I think also does the same thing and GCC
will just double the size so obviously
doubling is good in the sense that
you'll have fewer allocations if you're
just iterating through a list like this
and you're just repeatedly adding
elements at the expense of potentially
over allocating memory and actually we
can see this in action with our
breakpoint so over here you can see
we're trying to push back an element and
then where do we go into in place one at
back and if we just go up the core stack
we'll see the allocation over here but
right before that we have a new capacity
variable which comes from calculate
growth and if we take a look at that
what does it do it's got this geometric
variable over here which is old capacity
Plus old capacity / 2 right so we're
adding 50% and that determines our new
capacity so what that means is that the
capacity of this Vector goes from 0 to 1
that's one allocation when we add the
first element then from zero to well we
can't have 1.5 so two so that's two
allocations when we have the second
element then from 2 to well 2 + 50% is 3
to three when we have three elements
then from three to 1.5 I guess round it
up to five right so basically to add
these five elements we need four
allocations of memory so just set the
size first and then do your push back
and that's really easy to do you just
need to call this function called
Reserve five that's it what that does is
it says I want enough space for five
elements now and so if we run our
program with that
well that was a bit easy now we're down
to one
allocation now alternatively what you
can do is you can actually set the size
over here in the vector Constructor
that's the same thing as calling the
resize function so what's the difference
between reserve and resize well Reserve
will just Reserve that memory for you so
it will just basically change the
capacity of the vector to be five so not
the amount of elements currently in
there but just the capacity but resize
will actually set the number of elements
in inside Vector to five so basically
that means that we now have five
instances of the data struct inside this
Vector just constructed with the default
Constructor and so if we try and do this
code now we'll be pushing in five more
so we'll have a total of 10 so in this
case we actually have to go into our
original code and change
it to just be this we're setting each
element to this now instead of adding a
new element and that gives us the same
result so over here in our Tetris
example our real world example over here
with' moved tiles which we end up
pushing back into we would just either
set tiles. size as the actual parameter
over here in the Constructor if we
wanted to resize or just Reserve this
amount because tiles. size is going to
be how many we need I think it's just
four in this case but of course you
could argue that there's no reason for
us to actually default construct a whole
bunch of these data struct instances
only to override them so I would
probably prefer using the reserve
function in this case so that's it one
allocation are we done no because
there's actually something else going on
here and that's one of the reasons why I
decided to use a struct instead of just
a primitive type and that is copying
copying this stuff we have been
concerned with just allocations thus far
but what we should also be concerned
with is copies so at the moment data
doesn't actually have a copy Constructor
so let's add a copy Constructor to data
and I'm going to print out this copied
text over here maybe copied data and
then we'll also have a copy count
which I will increment so let's have a
look at our copy count now I do want to
mention that in this case you know data
is a a very simple struct we just have
an integer it's stored like in the
actual struct memory itself that's the
only thing we're storing it could be
something that perhaps stores a vector
of its own and a vector contains a heap
allocated block of memory meaning that
if we copy this data struct instance
we're actually causing an allocation
because we need to copy that Vector into
a new one as well so we're trying to
avoid this we're trying to minimize the
amount of copies that we need to make so
let's have a look thus far how many we
actually have and you can see we still
have five copies now it's better than
what it was if we get rid of Reserve we
have 15 copies and if we get rid of our
con reference in the print Vector
function we have a sickening 20 copies
so we have made some improvement however
wouldn't it be good if it was like well
I don't know zero is zero too much to
ask for so let's put back our const
reference and then over here I'm going
to bring back our Reserve which brings
us back down to five copies and so the
first step here is to figure out where
our copies are coming from and for that
you can do the same thing that we did
with this allocation function over here
and that is by just sticking a break
point into this copy Constructor make
sure you're running in debug by the way
and over here you can see that it's
coming from this line over here and the
reason why is because we're actually
constructing this instance of the data
struct here in this stack frame in this
scope and then we're copying it back
into the vector right so this is really
similar to what's happening over here
inside Tetris as well it's just it's
spread out onto two lines we're first
creating the struct instance over here
and then we're pushing it back into the
vector thus obviously copying it from
here into the vector it just looks a
little bit more sneaky when it's done
like this without an actual variable and
L value being created and that's why we
use a different function called imp
Place back and what imp Place back does
is it lets you specify the the
parameters of the Constructor so instead
of giving this Vector the actual data
object we just give it the parameters of
the object we want to construct and it
will do the construction for us inside
its own memory so we'll get rid of data
and if we had more parameters you know
we just specify them like this and it
will just forward them along and
construct that data instance already in
place in its kind of final memory now
you can also do this why because we have
copy Constructors and copy Constructors
take in the very object that we are
right because we're copying from another
object so therefore this actually still
works you can see I can go from push
back to and place back with no real
change but the magic obviously comes
from actually forwarding along those
Constructor arguments and so if I run
this zero copies one allocation and zero
copies that's the dream now I would be a
little bit sneaky here if I didn't
actually talk about moving rather than
copying because whilst all we can see
here if we reverse our code so we're
back to push back here all we can see
here is that writing code like this
causes a copy and that's bad the reason
why this is happening is because our
data struct doesn't have a move
Constructor if we add a move Constructor
so I'll just copy the copy Constructor
haha take that and then I will add in a
move Constructor let's go ahead and also
add a move count in this case it's not
going to matter there's not going to be
a difference between the copy
Constructor and the move Constructor but
obviously if we had say a vector or
something like hip memory like a pointer
to hip memory then we would just take
the actual pointer rather than copying
all the elements because we're not
creating a new Fresh copy we're just
moving kind of from one place to another
which is obviously much faster if you
don't know anything about moving in C++
move sematics that kind of stuff this
scary looking r value reference then I
have a couple videos in my C++ series
about that so I'll have them linked up
there so we'll do moved data instead and
then we will print that
out so in that case if we actually take
a look at this you can see we do a of
moved data instead and we have zero
copies but five moves so yes moving is
much better than copying it's not
technically I guess available on on
every class CU you actually have to add
it yourself obviously the standard
template Library will have that sorted
for things like strings that you might
want to move instead of copy however you
know what's even better than five moves
Zero moves and so the way you do that is
Again by using a place back which will
construct the object in place which you
should always prefer to do and you get
one allocation zero copies Zero moves
and that ladies and gentlemen is the
dream so in summary step one do you need
to use an STD Vector if you can use an
SD array which actually now that I think
about it we've ignored step one here
because in this case we absolutely don't
need a vector so let me show you how to
change this into an array this would
just be array five none of this and then
instead of in place back we would just
do kind of the same thing we did with
the vector resize where we just set the
element to data I like that and we're
done now this gives us an error in this
case because I actually need to add that
operator but just ignore that so this is
really step one because guess what this
isn't going to be one allocation it's
going to be zero allocations cuz they're
just going to be stack allocations not
Heap allocations which is an even better
dream than what we had before so step
one do you need to use an SCD Vector if
not don't use it step two do you know
roughly at least how many elements
you're actually going to have in that
Vector up front before you start adding
them one thing I didn't mention here by
the way is the fact that you can do this
kind of in increments right so if you
know you need a th000 for this and you
might need a th000 later you don't have
to do 2,000 at once you can just do a
th000 and then increase that like double
it yourself basically because maybe the
1.5 times the 50% that msvc is adding is
going to make it so that you have to do
like two or three uh extra allocations
instead of just one if you actually know
how much it's going to increase by so
basically try and manage the size the
capacity Yourself by either allocating
up front by calling the reserve or the
resize function or creating the vector
with the size in the Constructor like
this or by doing that later on in your
program and step three avoid copies
avoid moves use and place back don't use
push back like ever I don't really think
there's a huge reason to use push back
at all I think just replace push back
with imp Place back which again you
still need to use properly meaning if
this in place back was Data like this
like it was for push back then that
would function the exact same way as
push back so you still need to make sure
you're actually forwarding those
arguments along like that and that will
make sure that you avoid copies and and
moves and just construct the object in
place which by the way copies obviously
can contribute to allocations because if
you're copying an object that has Heap
allocated memory inside it is going to
have to allocate more memory for the new
copy so hopefully this is a nice little
guide to all of you if I missed anything
let me know in the comment section below
I could have probably mentioned that if
you're creating a new Vector within a
function and trying to return that how
that plays along with like return value
optimization there's some other things
we could discuss but I think in general
this is a a decently comprehensive guide
on how everyone should be using SCD
Vector at least compared to what I've
been seeing with all the code that
people have been sending me if you guys
enjoy this video then please hit the
like button let me know in the comment
section below do you want to see more of
this let me know what you think I should
cover next and I'll see you next time
goodbye